<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
	<title>The Case of the Thswane University of Technology Freedom Toaster</title>
	<sect1>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>South Africa, 2005. A developing nation struggling to shake off its part-apartheid
			shackles stands at a technological watershed. With a burgeoning population of 46.9 million<footnote>
				<para>StatsSA - Key findings: P0302 - population estimates</para>
			</footnote>, and an unemployment rate of 26.2 percent<footnote>
				<para>StatsSA - Labour force survey - 2004</para>
			</footnote>, South Africans are technologically divided. Those with access to technology
			are more readily able to secure high-income positions, while the technologically
			illiterate are increasingly sidelined. It’s a classic case of the rich getting richer,
			with the poor getting poorer. </para>
		<para>The South African government has made known how high an importance it places on income
			inequality and the equitable distribution of wealth. Studies have indicated that South
			Africa has a Gini coefficient for per capita income at around 0.7. When plotted on a
			Lorenz curve, this tells us that 80% of South Africa’s wealth is controlled by 27% of
			the population.</para>
		<para>When it comes to bridging the technological divide, several government programs are in
			place to promote the accessibility of computers in rural and developing areas, but there
			is still a great need for increased technology penetration. While complete technological
			integration on a real level into every South African community may only be a dream,
			promoting technological literacy on a grass-roots level is a vital component of
			empowerment.</para>
		<para>Ultimately, technology is expensive. Internet access under Telkom’s monopoly is
			restrictive due to the high prices, software licenses are costly, computers often cost
			more than an entire household's earnings and in some places even reliable access to
			electricity cannot be secured.</para>
		<para>Despite the obstacles there exists a huge demand for technological access and
			literacy, particularly among the emerging middle-class composed primarily of the
			historically disadvantaged. With technological competency fast becoming a prerequisite
			for any sort of skilled labour, making technology cheaply and widely available is a
			social and economic priority.</para>
		<para>While the chief problem associated with computer literacy will always be cost, a
			substantial portion of the expenditure incurred can be negated by switching to Free and
			Open Source Software (FOSS). However, open source software has its own drawbacks,
			particularly in the unique South African context. Without a reliable, fast internet
			connection, many open source applications and operating systems are all but
			inaccessible.</para>
	</sect1>
	<?pagebreak?>
	<sect1>
		<title>Overview</title>
		<para>FOSS is a viable alternative to licensing proprietary software, but has several key
			drawbacks within the South African context.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>The local market is dominated by traditional thinking when it comes to
					software usage, and as such, expensive, proprietary, closed source software is
					preferred.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Complete distributions of open source software, particularly operating
					systems, are often large and unwieldy, making them difficult to download through
					antiquated modem and ISDN technology.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Reliable, cheap internet in South Africa is all but non-existent; only a tiny
					percentage of the population can download FOSS.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Open source software is perceived as being difficult to use, with a
					substantial learning curve.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Analysis of the Freedom Toaster</title>
		<para>The Freedom Toaster was created to address the shortcomings of the open source model
			in the South African context. While FOSS is hugely popular in much of the world, its
			growth in South Africa has been stunted by the backward state of the South African
			telecommunications industry.</para>
		<para>FOSS relies heavily on the internet. Not only is the internet the primary means of
			distributing FOSS, but it serves - through forums, message boards and email discussion -
			as an arena for FOSS users to contribute back into the community. In an environment such
			as South Africa, with its limited and expensive internet access it hardly seems
			surprising that the uptake of FOSS is lagging behind other developing countries. </para>
		<para>In order to fully understand the need the Freedom Toaster fulfils in South Africa, a
			short overview of the South African internet situation needs to be presented. The South
			African telecommunications market is for all intents and purposes, a monopoly. The only
			fixed line provided is the former state-owned Telkom. Although Telkom has recently gone
			public, a significant portion of the company is still government owned, and as such, is
			plagued by many of the negative traits associated with a government-run enterprise such
			poor customer service, an ineffective administrative bureaucracy and a reluctance to
			move away from obsolete technology and procedures.</para>
		<para>As the only fixed line operator, Telkom has a virtual stranglehold on the South
			African internet community. Telkom recently launched its digital subscriber line (DSL)
			offering, a move that was hoped would foster the spread of FOSS locally, but
			unfortunately, this has not been the case.</para>
		<para>The problem lies with Telkom’s pricing of its DSL offering and its bandwidth usage
			structure. Firstly, although DSL may be synonymous with speed in the rest of the world,
			Telkom’s fastest DSL offering is a paltry 1024 kilobit line, giving an effective
			download speed of around 100 kilobytes per second, a far cry from residential cable and
			DSL packages in the United States and Europe, which are up to 100 times faster.</para>
		<para>Apart from the relatively low speeds, in order to discourage what Telkom terms ‘abuse’
			of the DSL network, subscribers are restricted to how much network traffic they can
			accumulate in a month. Once a user exceeds his or her bandwidth limit for the month,
			they are ‘capped’, and their service is effectively suspended. Additional bandwidth can
			be purchased from Telkom, which in effect serves as the sole wholesaler of DSL
			bandwidth, but it is prohibitively expensive to do so.</para>
		<para>For example, the latest version of the Debian operating system consists of two DVD
			images totalling 8.48 gigabytes, a hefty sum of data. Using Telkom’s 1024 HomeDSL
			package (the fastest available) and Telkom Internet’s Premium ISP offering would incur
			the following costs:</para>
		<informalequation>
			<mediaobject>
				<textobject>
					<para>R680.00 monthly rental fee + three Advanced Shaped TelkomInternet surfing
						packages @ R269.00 = R1487.</para>
				</textobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</informalequation>
		<para>By comparison, Bulldog Broadband, a broadband provider in the UK charges £40.00 per
			month for uncapped DSL, so there’s no need with such a service provider to purchase
			additional bandwidth at all. At current exchange rates, £40.00 equates to R470.40. Such
			a comparison is not entirely accurate though – Bulldog Broadband subscribers not only
			enjoy unlimited bandwidth, but other benefits as well, such as a free DSL router,
			something Telkom sells to its subscribers for R799.00.</para>
		<para>It’s also worth mentioning that the Bulldog Broadband service mentioned above is eight
			times faster than Telkom’s fastest DSL offering, so the 8.48gb Debian download that
			would take you an entire day on Telkom’s DSL would be done within three hours on Bulldog
			Broadband.</para>
		<para>While broadband has catalysed the FOSS movement in Europe, the United States and much
			of the rest of the world, Telkom’s poor DSL offering has served to effectively choke the
			uptake of both FOSS and the open source mentality in South Africa. </para>
		<para>Enter the Freedom Toaster, the apparent solution to many of South Africa’s open source
			distribution woes. The Freedom Toaster is essentially a FOSS vending machine; users
			bring their own blank CD or DVD discs and select software to 'toast' to the disc. The
			process is expedited by a user-friendly touch-screen interface that ensures even novice
			users can select and burn the software they require.</para>
		<para>The Freedom Toaster's selection of software is not limited to Linux distributions.
			Software such as the OpenCD and OpenOffice.org is available as well. The OpenCD contains
			a wealth of free Windows software such as Firefox and Thunderbird, which serve as free
			alternatives to Internet Explorer and Outlook. The selection of Windows-compatible
			software on the Freedom Toaster makes it an invaluable tool for those who have opted to
			stay with Microsoft Windows, but who require low-cost, functional desktop utilities and
			applications.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Implimentation</title>
		<para>By placing Freedom Toasters in strategic locations, the Shuttleworth Foundation has
			attempted to maximise the effectiveness of the Freedom Toaster concept. One such Toaster
			is located at the Tshwane University of Technology, Pretoria campus.</para>
		<para>The Tshwane University of Technology (TUT) is the largest residential higher education
			institution in South Africa, with more than 51 000 students. It is positioned to meet
			the higher education needs of different communities in South Africa, with well-equipped
			campuses in Pretoria and other areas.</para>
		<para>The TUT Pretoria campus was chosen as a Freedom Toaster location for several reasons:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Its sizable student base</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>TUT is South Africa’s largest technical tertiary educational institution, with
					highly-rated degree programs in computer-dependent fields such as Information
					and Communication Technology</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The proliferation of computer-related courses offered mean a large percentage
					of the students are computer literate or require computer literacy skills</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Its modern computer facilities and computer training programs promote computer
					use among students and public alike</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>The TUT offers a total of R170 million in student grants and loans every year, making
			it one of the most accessible tertiary educational facilities in the country. As a
			result of this financial aid, a significant portion of the University’s students come
			from historically disadvantaged backgrounds, meaning the Freedom Toaster is in a
			position to serve not only the academic community at large, but play its part in
			directly bridging the digital divide.</para>
		<para>With many of its students coming from lower-income backgrounds, the Freedom Toaster at
			the TUT is able to provide students with free, effective, easy-to-use open software such
			as OpenOffice.org. Those students who have computers at home are now able to install
			free software to replace their expensive, proprietary licensed software, while those new
			to computers can not only receive basic computer literacy training at the TUT, but
			through the Freedom Toaster can acquire software for their own use.</para>
		<para>This combination of technology training and accessible FOSS is highly effective in
			equipping students with the software and skills necessary to complete their studies.
			With the University’s focus on technology, having both accessible and affordable
			training and software is key to promoting computer literacy among the student base.</para>
		<para>The TUT also offers distance correspondence programs, a feature that integrates well
			with the Freedom Toaster. Students registering for distance learning can come to the
			campus for registration and make use of the Freedom Toaster to obtain software such as
			OpenOffice.org (for desktop publishing) and Mozilla’s Firefox and Thunderbird (for
			internet browsing and emailing other students and lecturers). </para>
		<para>The Freedom Toaster doesn’t just benefit the large and varied student base – educators
			and the general public make use of the Freedom Toaster at the TUT as well. With regular
			seminars and training hosted at the University, the Freedom Toaster serves the general
			populace, while educators and those using the campus’s library facilities are encouraged
			to make use of the Freedom Toaster for their software needs.</para>
		<para>Considering the TUT’s diverse and varied student base, the Freedom Toaster represents
			a prime opportunity to bridge the digital divide and make software available to the
			previously disadvantaged in a highly effective manner. The relationship between the TUT
			and the Freedom Toaster is a model for how academic institutions can further their aims
			of higher education and government’s aims of empowerment through the implementation of
			the Freedom Toaster. </para>
	</sect1>
</article>
