<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [

]>
<article>
  <title>Freedom Toaster</title>

  <subtitle>Conceptual Experiences - Host Case Study</subtitle>

  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Whenever a new concept is created and is introduced to a wider
    audience there is great potential for misunderstanding. Many people do not
    have the time to sit down and explore a new issue for themselves. Instead
    they rely on other people to inform them about the basics, and then they
    'make up their minds' about the concept.</para>

    <para>The Freedom Toaster and the concepts behind it are foreign to many
    people, both in South Africa and around the world. In order to better
    understand what the Freedom Toaster is and what benefits hosting
    organisations can gain from being a host to a Freedom Toaster we will
    present ten different potential hosting experiences. Some of these will be
    stories about people, some will be interviews with a Freedom Toaster host,
    and some will be mental explorations of the potentials within a specific
    environment. As the Freedom Toaster project is still in it's infancy and
    only available in South Africa at present, most of these hosting
    experiences will be projections and extrapolations rather than hard
    factual experiences.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>East London - RSA</title>

    <para>Let's take a quick trip to East London and imagine a Freedom Toaster
    being used there. Who would host it? Who would use it? What benefits would
    they receive? Come, join me in this experience....</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>The Place</title>

      <para>East London is a fascinating place. It is a busy ocean port (with
      the Daimler Chrsyler manufacturing plants located there), as well as a
      multicultural business and education hub. All sorts of people live in
      East London, those who want to surf the ocean waves... those who want to
      study further... business people involved in importing and exporting...
      business people involved in small local businesses... people in the
      entertainment industry... people who play golf, or fish, or drive fast
      cars. There are also people of community vision, like Elias - an owner
      of an Internet Café in the city centre.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>The Host</title>

      <para>Elias is a proud Freedom Toaster Host. He keeps the Freedom
      Toaster machine in the window of his shop, and is willing to speak about
      it with anyone who asks. His Internet Café runs on Free and Open Source
      (FOSS) software (Red Hat Fedora Core 4 to be precise), and he himself
      has programmed some of the programs to suit his business needs. He has
      two main servers that are connected via ADSL to the Internet, and has
      networked the 10 other workstations to connect through those two
      servers. Elias's two assistants, Jason and Xolani, did not know about
      Linux when they were hired, but very quickly adapted to it, and now are
      learning to install and configure so of the other distributions as
      well.</para>

      <para>Elias studied accounting and business at a local technicon, and
      had a friend, Zane, in his class who used Linux (Red Hat) on his home
      computer. When Elias was planning to open his Internet Café he phoned
      Zane and asked about the licensing fees and the installation costs of
      various operating systems. They both decided that it was worth
      investigating Linux distributions and comparing them with the other
      operating systems on the market.</para>

      <para>For Elias, installing the Red Hat Fedora Core 4 operating system
      made good business sense. The software itself was operated on a free
      license, and there was a company in town who supported Red Hat, so if he
      ran into a problem he could call them in to fix it. Elias started his
      Internet Café with four computers and one printer. His first clients
      just wanted to check email, type documents, and print them. They were
      not even aware that they were using a free license word processor
      (OpenOffice.org) and e-mail program (Thunderbird).</para>

      <para>When Elias heard about the Shuttleworth Foundation's Freedom
      Toaster he was very exited! "This is a dream come true for my
      community!" he told his staff the next day. "Now anyone who come to my
      Café can share in my success!". Elias and Zane got together and invested
      their own money into the production of their Freedom Toaster, following
      the instructions of the 'CookBook' produced by people involved in the
      project. It was a happy day when they were able to switch it on and
      toast their first OpenOffice.org CD for a customer.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>The Benefits to the Internet Café</title>

      <para>The Freedom Toaster's orange and black profile stands out as you
      approach Elias' shop. You can see the 'Internet Café' sign painted on
      the window, but your eye catches the Toaster. Elias has often had people
      come in and ask what it is... and then use one of his computers to type
      on so that they can see how the OpenOffice.org suite works, or what the
      Thunderbird e-mail program looks like. Most don't have their own
      computers, but are exited that they are using a computer that runs
      something the Shuttleworth Foundation is supporting. Some business men
      and women who have used the Internet Café for their e-mail have asked
      Elias if they can install this software on their business computers so
      that they can use it for their companies.</para>

      <para>The students from the High School up the road often come to Elias
      Internet Café. Since he put the Freedom Toaster up they have been
      bringing more and more of their friends, and even their mothers and
      fathers. Elias' business has grown because so many people are talking
      about the Freedom Toaster and Elias.</para>

      <para>Elias plans to open a Linux support company sometime soon, so he
      is encouraging Jason and Xolani to learn as much as they can. He hopes
      to get his wife will also be involved, maybe even in teaching people how
      to use computers. He is a man of community vision.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Benefits to Customers</title>

      <para>Some of Elias' customers don't care what they use, as long as it
      works. Others want to know more. When they explore all the software
      available on the Freedom Toaster they wonder that it is all there for
      free. Many students have toasted the Project Gutenberg DVD to use at
      their school computer labs. Many business people have toasted the
      OpenOffice.org CD and are using it at work, no longer worried about the
      cost of a proprietary office suite.</para>

      <para>According to Elias, however, the most important benefit to his
      customer is that they can see something happening in their community
      that they can benefit from. They are being empowered to learn for
      themselves.</para>

      <para>(The characters and businesses in this section are not real, they
      are presented in this manner so that you can experience the potentials
      encapsulated in the Freedom Toaster project)</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Rio - Brazil</title>

    <para>[The places and characters in this article are fictional - the
    opinions and ideas are representative of comments and responses of real
    people]</para>

    <para>It's pasted on posters all over the mall, 'Rio Computers' Freedom
    Toaster is HERE!'. Juan Marco, the shop owner, has been waiting for the
    construction of his Freedom Toaster to be completed for just over a week
    now, and finally it's done. They delivered the last plastic coverings this
    morning and the shop sales team were able to assemble the Toaster before
    they opened their doors to the public. It's standing right by the door,
    next to the payment tills, a bright orange beacon.</para>

    <para>Now, you might be asking yourself, "what is this Freedom Toaster?"
    Well, to put it quite simply, it is a digital bandwidth substitute, a
    vending machine that allows you to toast blank CDs with Free and Open
    Source Software (FOSS) and other free license content. Instead of
    downloading software or information from the Internet you can write it to
    a CD-ROM and use it on your own computer.</para>

    <para>There has been a lot of talk among the staff about the impact the
    Freedom Toaster will have on their business. Some see it as just a
    marketing gimmick, there for the next six months and then gone. Others see
    greater potential in the Freedom Toaster, and they see Juan Marco as a
    pioneer FOSS and the other free license content to the people of
    Rio.</para>

    <para>Petros Alvierese, one of the store's salespeople, has noticed that
    more people are looking into the window of the shop, to see the bright
    orange Freedom Toaster, and then coming in and asking questions. Some have
    bought CDs and toasted a LiveCD Linux distribution (a bootable CD with a
    Linux operating system that runs from the CD) to try on their office and
    home computers. Others have toasted the OpenOffice.org CD and used it on
    their machines. They couldn't afford to upgrade their office suit (and
    OpenOffice.org's suite has Spanish immediately available, not as an extra
    addon feature). Petros has been speaking to customers who are wanting to
    buy compete computer systems, but are not able to afford the computer
    hardware and pay for all the software licenses for the operating system
    and office suits available. Now that the Freedom Toaster is available some
    of the customers have been asking about installing one of the operating
    systems available from the Toaster. Using free license software these
    customers can afford to get a complete entry level computer. Without the
    free license software they couldn't.</para>

    <para>Susanna Falonso, a sales clerk, thinks that the Freedom Toaster has
    brought in more people today. She has seen quite a few people using the
    touch screen menu and then asking one of the salespeople some questions.
    Many have bought some CDs and come to her till and paid for them before
    toasting something for them to take home for themselves. Susanna thinks
    that Juan Marco is a very clever man, and that this Freedom Toaster idea
    is very good for the shop, and very good for her community. She is already
    using the OpenOffice.org suite on her work computer, and has decided to
    toast a copy of the suite to give to her husband for his computer at work
    (she knows that he has wanted to upgrade the office suite they use, but
    can't afford all the license fees for the 20 computers in the company he
    works for). She is very happy with having the Freedom Toaster right next
    to the sales counter, as she likes smiling to people and having them smile
    back.</para>

    <para>Juan Marco is planning on getting a few more staff members in his
    technical support section. The new staff will be Linux specialists who can
    support the customers who have installed Linux operating systems, like
    Redhat, Mandriva, or Suse. Rio Computers has recently been granted the
    tender for installing 50 computers in the local government school two
    blocks up the road from the mall. The teachers and students will be using
    the computers for typing, printing, email, Internet, and some database and
    spreadsheet functions. Juan has told them about the Freedom Toaster, and
    they are thinking of installing one on their premises as well. They will
    be using the K12 distributed Linux operating system, specifically
    developed by the open source community for schools, and will be using
    material from the Project Gutenberg (a CD or DVD distribution of pubic
    domain books and texts - from literature to scientific treaties) in their
    classes.</para>

    <para>The Freedom Toaster is HERE! For Juan Marco the posters all around
    the Mall are the realisation of a dream come true. For the staff of Rio
    Computers it is the beginning of a new area of their business. The Freedom
    Toaster is HERE!</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Nyamuna - Malawi</title>

    <para>[This article contains fictional characters and places, but the
    projected opinions are from real people]</para>

    <para>There is a place that people can go to in Nyamuna, Malawi where
    community really matters. The people who work there are proud of their
    community, happy to help, glad to be involved. It's not only the staff who
    are proud of their community, the community leaders, the mayor, the
    council men and women, even the patrol officers are proud of this
    community. At the community centre in Nyamuna people's lives
    change.</para>

    <para>There are many projects being run at the community centre, and many
    people who come in and out of its doors everyday. One of these projects
    involves the Freedom Toaster, a concept started in South Africa,
    championed by the Shuttleworth Foundation (started by Mark Shuttleworth -
    first African in Space!). At first it was hard to understand just how
    important the Freedom Toaster was. No one knew what it was or what it did.
    Let me tell you of how we heard about it and what we did to get one of our
    own.</para>

    <para>Project Director Punjabi was in Cape Town, South Africa at a
    conference and on the Thursday afternoon when they had a two hour break he
    went down to the waterfront shopping area. There he found the MTN Science
    centre and went inside to look. There he saw his first Freedom Toaster.. a
    'bring and burn' your own CDs type of vending machine. He went up to it
    and read the different screens that the machine scrolled through, and
    found out that this Freedom Toaster had 13 different versions of Linux
    that he could copy to his own discs for free... and the Project Gutenberg,
    the OpenOffice.org CD, and other Free and Open Source (FOSS) CDs. He was
    amazed that afternoon in Cape Town, amazed that all this information was
    freely available for anyone who had access to a computer to use for free.
    He knew that the Community Centre in Nyamuna would really benefit from one
    of these. They had ten computers in the centre, and a project to train
    people on how to use a mouse and how to type, but with access to a Freedom
    Toaster they could take that even further! Mr Punjabi knew that if people
    were able to own their own software disks they would feel more involved,
    more able to share what they knew and what they had. He also knew that
    there would be another project later in the year that would bring in
    second hand computers to the Centre... that would be a greater opportunity
    for the community if they had a Freedom Toaster.</para>

    <para>Not many people in Nyamuna have access to the Internet. Quite a few
    have computers, especially those with their own businesses. There was no
    way that they would be able to download the software and information that
    was part of the Freedom Toaster's system.</para>

    <para>Project Director Punjabi came back from Cape Town as a very excited
    man. He had spoken with Nyamuna from the Science Centre and had been given
    the 'Cookbook', the instruction manual for building a Freedom Toaster. Mr
    Punjabi had also been in contact with one of the Community Centre
    supporters, Mr Kaliman, and had already got clearance for the materials
    needed to build the Toaster. His excitement was contagious! Soon everyone
    at the Community Centre knew that a Freedom Toaster was being built, and
    they wondered what it would do. A week after Mr Punjabi returned from Cape
    Town he announced an opening ceremony for the Freedom Toaster. He invited
    the Mayor, the police chief, the Headmaster, the Doctor,and all the
    teachers and students and anyone who would be able to come on a Saturday
    afternoon. The Community Centre was packed with people. Mr Punjabi spoke
    about his dream that someday everyone in this community would be able to
    use a computer, either one of their own, or one in the community centre's
    computer lab. He told them about free license software, and about the open
    source concept of producing software. One of the teachers from the school
    raised his hand and asked whether his computer science students would be
    able to see the code for an email system (the school had been donated 20
    new and up-to-date computers for their computer lab). Mr Punjabi said that
    they now had source code not just for an email system, but for whole
    operating systems, mp3 players, word processors, and more! Those who were
    advanced enough in their studies would be able to create their own
    versions with their own customisation and code. Mrs Selune asked about
    software to type documents. Mr Punjabi told them about the OpenOffice.org
    project. He told the teachers and the students about the Project
    Gutenberg, how they now had access to the great literature of the world,
    just for the price of a blank CD or DVD (about 20 Rupees).</para>

    <para>We learnt a lot that day. We saw one man's passion bring a concept
    from another country and make it ours. We now have high school students
    who have contributed to the security code of Evolution, an email system.
    They did it as a class project last term. We have students in the
    community centre every afternoon, bringing their disks to read 'Hamlet' by
    Shakespeare as part of their literature class. Business people in town
    have come and toasted their own copies of SuSE and Mandrake, and other
    Linux operating systems. We now also have an Internet connection at the
    Community centre, and soon we hope to open an Internet café in
    town.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>New Delhi - India</title>

    <para>[The characters in this article are fictional, the sentiments and
    opinions are based are on comments by real people]</para>

    <para>A library is not only a place where you can borrow books. It is also
    a place to learn more about yourself, more about your community, and more
    about life. The library is a place of expanding yourself. Mrs Gandhi knows
    this, and acts on it everyday. She is the Head Librarian at Dr Zakir
    Hussain Memorial in New Delhi, India. She has been the Head Librarian for
    fifteen years, and has seen so a lot of change over the years that she has
    worked there.</para>

    <para>We asked Mrs Gandhi what she thought of the Freedom Toaster, and
    what benefits the Library had gained by hosting one. She very candidly
    told us that at first she couldn't really understand what the Freedom
    Toaster was all about. One of the Library Trustees had come to her with an
    article from the Shuttleworth Foundation describing the Freedom Toaster
    concept and the difference that Freedom Toasters were making in parts of
    South Africa. The Trustee had been very excited about the possibility of
    creating a Freedom Toaster for .... Library. The Board of Trustees voted
    to become a Freedom Toaster host, and approached the Local Development
    Fund director for additional funding. Once the Freedom Toaster had been
    installed, however, Mrs Gandhi told us that she became an avid supporter
    very quickly.</para>

    <para>"The greatest benefit to this library that I have seen since we put
    the Toaster in the foyer out there is the increase in people coming to our
    library" Mrs Gandhi tells us. "When we first installed the Freedom Toaster
    we put posters up in all the windows of the Library. All the teachers came
    and asked us what it was about. Then the children came and wanted to know
    how to use the Freedom Toaster. They toasted themselves copies of the
    Project Gutenberg... then they brought their parents to see the machine! I
    remember one of the parents came and asked why it was all for free. He
    'didn't want his children copying pirated software' he said. My, my, we
    had some fun explaining the concept of free license software and open
    source software that day. When he understood this he brought in his boss
    from work and together they toasted about five of the Linux distributions
    to try on their new computer at work. Eh, he was happy! People keep
    bringing other people to see it and use it, then they come back and ask us
    about joining the library. It seems that so many people have forgotten
    that we were here."</para>

    <para>During our conversation with Mrs Gandhi we also learnt that the
    Freedom Toaster had been used by one of the local schools as part of their
    technology project. The students had each been given an assignment about
    one or more aspect of the Freedom Toaster, from the physical hardware that
    made up the vending machine, to the software that ran the Toaster, and
    even the software and information that could be 'toasted' by the Freedom
    Toaster. Some of the other Librarians helped the students gather
    information, and got to know them very well during the course of the
    project. One of the girls in the class had always wanted to write poetry,
    and one of the librarians had shown her the collection of poetry in the
    Library, and the section on writing prose and poems. That girl went on to
    win a prize at the end of the year for one of her poems. The Freedom
    Toaster brought her to the library and connected her to her dream.</para>

    <para>The benefit of hosting the Freedom Toaster was also described in
    terms of benefiting the community as a whole. "We're never really sure of
    all the affects that we have as a Library within this community," Mrs
    Gandhi continues, "but with the focus of the Freedom Toaster we have seen
    some marvellous things happen. It stands there, straight and tall, as a
    symbol of upliftment for all who walk in here." Mrs Gandhi knows that a
    library is not just a place to find a book to read. She knows that her
    library is a meeting point in her community, and a resource of knowledge
    and challenge for all those who walk past or come inside. The Freedom
    Toasters is one of the tools that her library uses. Yours could
    too.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Johannesburg - RSA</title>

    <para>[This article is mostly fictional, but there is a Freedom Toaster at
    the Experience Centre of YFM at The Zone in Rosebank]</para>

    <para>Have you ever wondered what people at a radio station do all day? Do
    they just listen to music and make playlists for their shows? Do they sit
    around drinking coffee and smoking cigarettes or eating doughnuts when
    they are not speaking 'live'? Well, I got to see first hand what some DJs
    and Radio Station managers and staff do, when I interviewed them about the
    competition they were running, concerning the Freedom Toaster.</para>

    <para>If you walk into 'The Zone' at Rosebank, and find the YFM studios
    (one of the shops around the courtyard downstairs from the Sterkinekor
    Movies) you will see what looks like a bright orange vending machine
    behind the 5 or so computers in the Internet café portion of YFM's
    interactive centre. If you look more closely you will see a touch screen,
    and three CD/DVD writer drives, as well as the words "Freedom Toaster" on
    the orange portion of the machine. Take a step even closer and start
    reading the screen and you will find that you can bring your own CDs and
    write all sorts of software and information to them, for free. I'll tell
    you more about that software a little later...</para>

    <para>I first went to the reception and spoke with the secretary there,
    asking her who would best know why YFM was hosting a Freedom Toaster. She
    spoke on the phone with a few people and then informed me that I needed to
    go to the main offices (also at The Zone in Rosebank) and talk with
    Janice. While I was talking with the receptionist I saw quite a few radio
    personalities. Some were just getting some coffee, others were chatting
    about something that had happened during the morning show, and were
    laughing quite merrily about it. I then went to the main offices and spoke
    with Janice, who was one of the accounting managers of the station. She
    didn't know much about the Freedom Toaster, but she did know that the
    station had run a competition and that the Freedom Toaster had something
    to do with the competition. Janice also mentioned that although she had
    not had much to do with the competition, she was impressed with the
    response that the Station had from listeners during the competition. She
    put me in touch with Andrew.</para>

    <para>There is no doubt in my mind that Andrew was impressed with the
    response of the listeners to the concept of the Freedom Toaster. The
    competition ran for just over four weeks. Listeners had to phone in with
    answers to specific open source software questions. Anyone could go to the
    YFM experience centre at The Zone and find all the answers by using the
    Freedom Toaster. To win prizes, listeners had to phone in with the answers
    to the questions. There were quite a few days when up to 30 people phoned
    in during a ten minute period (with only 10 phone lines dedicated to the
    competition). In one sense, the competition was an educational campaign.
    People had to interact with the Freedom Toaster and with the software and
    other material on it. It was not enough to know computers in general. As
    the Freedom Toaster contained 13 different operating systems that could be
    toasted to blank CDs, the range of questions was large. Some questions
    would be fairly simple, while others were complex and required an in depth
    knowledge of a Linux system.</para>

    <para>From Andrew's perspective, the Freedom Toaster had brought greater
    listener participation. Many people had come to the YFM experience Centre
    at The Zone, and had not only found out more about the Freedom Toaster but
    had interacted with some of the presenters and DJs who were there. More
    people knew about the YFM experience centre and the Internet café, coffee
    bar, and games areas. Andrews knowledge of the Freedom Toaster was more
    geared to the specific answers to th questions of the competition. He knew
    that it had been pioneered by the Shuttleworth Foundation, that there were
    Freedom Toasters throughout South Africa (and one in Namibia). He knew
    about the concept of free license software and the open source philosophy
    (publishing source code for others to read and improve on). He also knew
    about Project Gutenberg, the electronic text library of pubic domain works
    (Shakespeare, Milton, Dante, Einstein, Poe, and thousands of other works
    of literature, fiction, poetry, science , maths, etc.).</para>

    <para>I did not find out what people do at a radio station all day, but I
    did find out that YFM has good interjection with it's listeners. They were
    able to communicate on various levels and with various types of medium
    (both radio and experience centre). The Freedom Toaster project benefited
    from this exposure, as did YFM.</para>
  </sect1>
<?pagebreak?>
  <sect1>
    <title>ShenZen - China</title>

    <para>[The characters of this article are fictional and situations are
    projections of what could be]</para>

    <para>ShenZen used to be just a small village before it's location on the
    China / Hong Kong border made it a prime place for major economic growth.
    Now it is a bustling city, with tens of thousands of people travelling in
    and out of it every day. It is a very busy place.</para>

    <para>ShenZen has a Freedom Toaster. A computer with CD and DVD burning
    capabilities that is set up in the shape of a vending machine. The Freedom
    Toaster is used to distribute Free and Open Source Software (FOSS) and
    other free content. In ShenZen the Freedom Toaster is in the main lounge
    of the Adult Education Centre. The Centre has three main goals. The first
    is simply to increase literacy among the adult population of ShenZen. This
    they do through free reading classes and local reading and writing
    competitions. Their second goal is to raise awareness of what teaching is
    available to adults, things like computer literacy, art classes, marshal
    arts, and typing classes. This is the area in which the Freedom Toaster
    has its primary effect. The last goal of the Adult Education Centre is to
    be a safe place for people to come to, to share their problems, receive
    counselling, and general community building and upliftment.</para>

    <para>The Adult Education Centre has had the Freedom Toaster for six
    months now, and they have adapted the main programme to suit there needs.
    They still have all the FOSS software that other Freedom Toaster's have,
    but they have added their own CD which contains all the reading and
    writing tutorials that they use (in Chinese). They have also added a CD
    image that contains tutorials for use when learning English as a second
    language. Since the Freedom Toaster was installed, more and more people
    have been asking to learn English, so the Centre has started giving
    classes again (they did four years ago but after four classes had
    graduated interest dwindled). One of the Centre's volunteers translated
    the Freedom Toaster's interface system into Mandarin, and other adult
    education centres are also now hosting Freedom Toasters of their
    own.</para>

    <para>The main use of the Freedom Toaster at the Adult Education Centre is
    the teaching Cd's, but many more people are becoming interested in the
    Linux distributions and in the OpenOffice.org suite, particularly as it
    has Chinese fonts and dictionaries. Those who can read and write English
    are also beginning to use the Project Gutenberg disks, particularly the
    parents of High School children. Those who do not have computers at home
    take the disks to work and print out a few chapters of a book each day to
    read. Others use the Adult Education Centre's small computer facility (6
    computers) when computer literacy classes are not in session. They are
    having fun reading some of the children's stories. Soon they will be
    reading some of the more advanced literature.</para>

    <para>It is interesting to note that the concept of free license software
    was difficult for some people at the Adult Education Centre to accept.
    They were used to paying for all the software that they used, and not
    being able to change any of the original code of the programs they were
    using. This has been challenged by the presence of the Freedom Toaster,
    for now they can go and toast their own copies of an operating system that
    contains all the tools they need to write documents, email, network, store
    data, and even play games. The manager for the Adult Education Centre had
    to have three training sessions with the staff of the Centre before they
    were fully comfortable with all that the Freedom Toaster had, and what
    effect it could have on their community. Now they are all eager to help
    when someone asks a question or asks for help with the Freedom Toaster.
    They have learnt a lot of new things too.</para>

    <para>One of the benefits of having the Freedom Toaster located in the
    main lounge is that it has become a focus point for the computer literacy
    classes. All the computers that are used to teach computer literacy are
    running software that is available on the Toaster. Even for people who
    don't have their own computers, it is still a major thrill to be able to
    toast one of the LiveCDs and take it with them so that when they get back
    to their job (or find one) they can illustrate their proficiency and their
    knowledge of computers in general. Many people talk about the FOSS on the
    Freedom Toaster. Some of the graduates of the computer literacy class have
    formed a Linux Users Club, and they meet every month at the Centre to
    discuss new developments and things that they have learnt.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Santiago - Chile</title>

    <para>[This article is a projection of possibilities, the characters and
    places are fictional]</para>

    <para>There are many different ways to make money, but one of the most fun
    is by helping people get what they want. When you see the joy and gladness
    that they express when they finally have it, that is priceless. My name is
    Amelio. I'm a 27 year old entrepreneur from Santiago in Chile. My bank
    thinks that I'm in the Internet Service Provider (ISP) business, but I'm
    really in the business of helping people have fun with their computers. I
    earn my money from the Internet, but my passion is for people.</para>

    <para>When I first started this business in 2001 there were only 7 other
    ISPs. Roughly 1.75 million people (out of 15 million) were Internet users
    in my country. That number is growing. Four years ago I hadn't heard of
    Linux, nor had I heard of Free and Open Source Software (FOSS). In 2002 I
    was surfing online while waiting for a take away order to arrive, and I
    read an article on one of the news sites about an operating system that
    you could download and run for free, called Linux. It caught my attention,
    so I clicked on the link and read some more about open source software.
    There were so many distributions (different flavours) of Linux, ranging
    from small systems that could fit on my 128Meg USB memory stick, to
    distributions 14 CDs or more is size, containing all sorts of business,
    graphics, multimedia, office, and entertainment software. I decided to try
    Linux out and did some research on which distribution to try first. I
    chose a Knoppix LiveCD, mainly because I could boot into the operating
    system straight from the CD without affecting the other software installed
    on my computer. This way I could play around with Linux and learn things
    about it and how to use it without having to format my harddrive and
    install a completely new system.</para>

    <para>It was a lot of fun to put the CD in, boot up and instantly see
    Linux at work. My screen and sound card were automatically configured, my
    network connections were setup, and I could save files onto the server in
    my office. I worked on documents in OpenOffice.org. I played around with
    XMMS (mp3 and multimedia player). Then tried the games that came bundled
    with Knoppix. What fun!</para>

    <para>When people came into my shop and into my office, asking about the
    services that we provided and asking about what software to use, I began
    to speak to a few of them about Linux. Most were very sceptical, but a few
    decided that it was investigating. Mr .... was one such customer. Together
    we installed some of the full desktop distributions, SuSE, Red Hat,
    Mandrake, Slackware, and explored the differences and ease of use. The
    basics that Mr ... needed were in every distribution, but he found
    Mandrake easier to use and configure, so we did the full installation and
    the online updates. In 2005 Mr ... was in Johannesburg, South Africa and
    was at the LinuxWorld Expo. There he saw a Freedom Toaster (a Free and
    Open Source 'bring and burn' vending machine). This was one that the
    Shuttleworth Foundation had at their stand, and the queue of people
    'toasting' was always quite long. Mr ... got more information from the
    staff behind the table, and brought it back to me. It is a fascinating
    idea. A machine that has Linux distributions and other free license
    content that can be burned to CDs and DVDs by the touch of the onscreen
    menu. The only cost is the blank CD or DVD used. The Shuttleworth
    Foundation see the Freedom Toaster as a solution for access to FOSS where
    there is low bandwidth or no Internet access.</para>

    <para>You know that I sell Internet bandwidth as a living. I know how many
    hours people spend on line, I know average download speeds. I have all
    those statistics from my own business. I know the frustrations of using
    dial in connections to try to download some of this software. I decided to
    find out if we could get a Freedom Toaster or something similar here in
    Chile. I went to the Freedom Toasters online site (www.freedomtoaster.org)
    and read what other people were doing and even had access to the
    'cookbook', the instruction manual on how to build one for yourself. What
    a great concept.. a cookbook for a toaster! My staff and I built one, and
    we installed it in our front office four months ago.</para>

    <para>In the first month we saw a lot of general interest from customers.
    They wanted to know what it was and what it did. I did a lot talking about
    Firefox and Thunderbird (FOSS Internet browser and email programs). Some
    of my core business customers came and made an appointment with me and
    asked a lot of questions. One of the problems that we discussed was who
    supported the software. One of the concepts of open source software is
    that a community of programmers deal with the code and the bugs and
    errors, so in a general sense there is a programming community supporting
    the software. These customers wanted something more local, someone that
    could call on the phone or email and get help from. That was when the idea
    for expanding my business came to me. I knew enough about Linux to help
    people install it and configure it. I also knew enough about the MS
    Windows FOSS on the Freedom Toaster to support it as well.</para>

    <para>Last month I opened my second business. I use the same office as my
    ISP business, but now I have three other people working with me. Two run
    the ISP side, and one helps me with local support for software available
    on the Freedom Toaster. We stock blank CDs and DVDs, so people can either
    bring their own blanks, or purchase the ones we stock. My business has
    already grown to the point where I'm thinking of employing another
    technician to work with us on the support side. Now I not only provide an
    Internet Service, but I also provide access to free license software for
    the computers that access the Internet, and support for that software. I'm
    a happy man, and so are my customers.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Grahamstown - RSA</title>

    <para>[While the characters, writer, and conversations of this article are
    imaginary, the Science Festival and the Shuttleworth Foundation's presence
    in Grahamstown are real]</para>

    <para>One of the most exciting events for the school children and
    residents of Grahamstown, South Africa, is the Science Festival held there
    every year. Most of the exhibitions are hosted at the Monument (an 1820
    settler's site that is now a huge auditorium with smaller theatres,
    exhibition rooms, and lobby space - perfect for exhibitions). All the big
    players are there; University science, geology, physics, chemistry,
    robotics, and other scientific specialist departments; Industry giants
    like SASOL, IBM, Hewlette Packard, Telkom, and Sony; local companies -
    computer shops, photo labs, food vendors, etc.</para>

    <para>This year the Science Festival also hosted the Freedom Toaster,
    usually located in the Shuttleworth Foundation's centre in Grahamstown.
    Students from Victoria Girls High School, Graeme College, and St Andrews
    High School all crowded the location of the Freedom Toaster in the lower
    lobby of the Monument Building. Although the schools have computer labs
    and Internet access, the connections are not fast enough for the
    downloading of full Linux operating systems or CD images of the OpenCD
    (Windows based free license opensource software). The Rhodes University
    computer science students and the information technology students also
    were intrigued by the idea and by the range of software that was available
    for 'toasting'.</para>

    <para>For those of you who are not familiar with the Freedom Toaster
    concept, let me briefly explain what it is and what is so important about
    it. The Freedom Toaster is a computer set up to look like a vending
    machine. It has a touch screen monitor and CD writer drives on the front.
    The unit has an orange and black exterior. The machine part of the Freedom
    Toaster is not the exciting part. What you are able to do with the Freedom
    Toaster is... you are able to bring your own blank CDs and write all sorts
    of free and open source software (FOSS) and other content to your discs.
    The Freedom Toaster is really a bandwidth substitute, a way of accessing
    free license content without needing access to the Internet. The Freedom
    Toaster has been developed by the ShuttleWorth Foundation and the open
    source community in South Africa. Currently it holds CD images of 13
    different Linux distributions, the OpenOffice.org CD, the OpenCD (a
    collection of Windows based opensouce applications), the Mozilla
    Firefox/Thunder Bird collection (the most popular feature rich Internet
    browser and email open source application), and the Project Gutenberg
    (collection of electronic texts of all the pubic domain [out of copyright]
    literature, fiction, science texts, general information books,..etc.) CD
    and DVD images.</para>

    <para>The computer science students from Rhodes University were already
    familiar with Linux, and many had already used Linux based systems for
    programming and testing purposes. What they were impressed with was the
    range of distributions available, from the single CD 'live' distributions
    (CD images that are bootable and run from he CD without having to write to
    the harddrive or interfere with the operating system already installed on
    the computer) through to the large 13 CDs of the Debian Sarge
    distribution. They were also impressed that the Freedom Toaster offered
    BSD, another opensource operating system, similar to Linux, but based on a
    different kernel (core system). Many of them toasted the larger
    distributions, as they had the largest variety of open source software
    ready to be installed.</para>

    <para>One of the drama students discovered that the Project Gutenburg DVD
    had the complete works of Shakespeare on, as well as the translations of
    many of the Greek plays. He told his Classics Professor, and soon the
    whole class were queueing up with their blank DVD-Roms, waiting to toast
    their own copies. While many of he students did own computers, those that
    didn't had plenty of access to the computer labs, and so they were also
    able to make full use of the information that was freely available from
    the Freedom Toaster.</para>

    <para>For some of the High School students it was just fun to toast some
    CDs at the science festival so that they could take the disks back to the
    dormitory and show their friends what they had done that day. Some of the
    games that come bundled on the LiveCD distributions (like Knoppix) are
    quite fun to play (even addictive to some...).</para>

    <para>One of the most touching experiences of the Freedom Toaster's booth
    at the science festival was the look on the children's faces when they
    realised that this machine didn't take money.. just blank CDs. The schools
    from across the Eastern Cape send bus loads of children to the festival,
    and it was amazing to see how quickly the high school students from all
    types of backgrounds and schools embraced the concept of the Freedom
    Toaster. There is a hunger for knowledge in the children of our nation.
    Many of them asked their teachers if it was possible to have a Freedom
    Toaster machine closer to where they lived (they had read the posters and
    pamphlets detailing the position of all the Freedom Toasters in South
    Africa and Namibia). I certainly hope that there will be many more hosts
    for Freedom Toasters across South Africa, and indeed around the
    world.</para>

    <para>On the last day of the Science Festival many of the local residence
    of Grahamstown were asking about the Shuttleworth Foundation Centre, and
    whether they would be able to access the Freedom Toaster at the Centre.
    The staff were very please to answer 'Yes!"</para>

    <para>If this year's Science Festival is anything to go by, the
    Shuttleworth Foundation will have to bring 3 machines to next years event,
    or find enough co-sponsors to put Freedom Toasters in all the main High
    Schools, libraries, and shopping centres around our great country. It was
    good to see that the open source community had something so positive to
    present at the festival. We were all enriched by it.</para>

    <para><emphasis>Report by Andrew Smythe - third year journalism student at
    Rhodes University.</emphasis></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Gabarone - Botswana</title>

    <para>[This article is fictional, but the opinions expressed and the
    possibilities explored are based on real people's opinions]</para>

    <para>There is an old african tale that is known in some parts of southern
    africa, which tells us of the great act of heroism that earned the leopard
    his spots. It was one of those hot windy days in the bush, the type that
    would make a bush fire very hot and fast. Most of the animals were nervous
    that morning, their instinct telling them that something was about to
    happen that would change their lives forever. The wise old monkey who all
    the animals reviered and came to when they were sick was sleeping high in
    his tree. The leopard was just a dull yellow colour before this day, and
    he (as usual) was all alone, stalking a young wart hog. The leopard was
    not liked by any of the other animals. He was very selfish and greedy, and
    looked quite ugly (unless you were another leopard I guess). Most animals
    walked the other way if they smelled his scent on the wind.</para>

    <para>It was mid afternoon when the first scent of fire came, wisps of
    smoke from over the hill, then came the sound of fire crackling through
    the grass. The wind pushed it relentlessly up the hill and over the top
    and down into the valley where the leopard lived. It came so fast that
    most of the animals just dropped what they were doing and ran for the
    safety of the river and the rocks next to the waterfall. The wise old
    monkey was left sleeping, high up in his tree, as all the animals forgot
    about him in their terror of the fire. Once they were at the river and
    were calming down, however, they looked around them for the wise old
    monkey, but he wasn't there. The leopard slinked out of the bush and sat
    down on a rock next to the water (there were to many animals there,
    protecting each other that he couldn't see a way to get a quick meal). He
    heard them talking about the wise old monkey. The wise old monkey had
    saved the leopards life when he was a kitten. He had a thorn in one of his
    paw pads that had gotten infected, and the wise old monkey had taken it
    out and put some leaves and honey on it until it was better. The leopard
    knew that the wise old monkey would die from the smoke if he didn't leave
    his tree, but the fire was already burning at the bottom of it. All the
    other animals were too terrified to do anything.</para>

    <para>The leopard made a decision then that changed his life, and the
    lives of the other leopards who have lived since then. He decided to
    rescue the wise old monkey. He ran along the branches of the trees, above
    the flames on the ground all around him, but as he got to the tree that
    the wise old monkey had been sleeping in he saw that the whole tree was
    catching alight. This tree was in bloom, and the flowers were catching on
    fire and falling off. There was only one thing to do if the wise old
    monkey was to be saved. The leopard ran through the rain of burning
    flowers and up into the higher branches where the wise old monkey was
    lying, almost suffocated by the smoke. The leopard picked him up in his
    powerful jaws and ran back through the burning flowers and flames. He got
    the wise old monkey safely to the river bank, but when he looked at
    himself he saw that his fur was burning. He leapt into the river, putting
    the flames out, and splashing enough water on the wise old monkey that he
    revived. As the leopard came out of the water all the other animals
    gasped! He was no longer an ugly plain yellow colour, instead he had dark
    brown and black imprints of the tree flowers all over his coat, making him
    look totally different. The wise old monkey picked up the leopard's right
    paw and raised it to the sky, saying "This day the leopard has gone
    through the fire and rescued wisdom! As his reward he has been granted a
    new coat, one that will forever protect him from the sight of the
    hunters." The other animals were grateful to the leopard for saving the
    wise old monkey, and they began to treat him with respect in the following
    months. The leopard was still often alone, but he was no longer so selfish
    and greedy. He wore his new coat with humbleness, for he knew that he was
    not anyone special. He had just been the one who was able to do something
    in that situation. Now if you see ever see a leopard, look closely at his
    spots and you will see the burn marks of the flowers, medals of bravery
    and courage for saving wisdom.</para>

    <para>You will hear this story being told by Amai Ndodwa at the Sisonkwe
    Community Arts Centre in Gabarone, Botswana. She is like the leopard in
    many ways. She went to a very expensive school and university when she was
    younger, and used what she learnt to make herself very rich, often at the
    expense of others. But one day she met a wise old woman from the same
    village that she had come from, and the wise old woman had sat her down
    and told her about the flames that were eating her heart day by day, the
    flames of greed and power. Through that conversation Amai Ndodwas life
    began to change. She had felt the loneliness that her greed had caused in
    her life. That was the year that she came to the community arts centre for
    the first time. She saw the paintings of many artists who expressed beauty
    and wisdom. She also saw herself in one of the paintings, a leopard, on
    fire...</para>

    <para>Her life changed that day, and she began to look for ways to bring
    help to other people, and bring information and wisdom to those in her
    community. She is part of the team that requested a Freedom Toaster for
    Sisonke Community Arts Centre. She saw one in Namibia when she was
    visiting there, and was able to see that access to the information that
    the Freedom Toaster contained would help many people in her community.
    That was the day she started the project that has now reached over 3000
    people in this part of Gabarone. The Freedom Toaster is a digital
    bandwidth substitute for free license and open source software. The idea
    was created in South Africa, under the care of the Shuttleworth
    foundation. It has CD images of many operating systems (Linux
    distributions and BSD), office programs, graphics programs, Internet
    applications, and the Project Gutenburg. Amai Ndodwa knew that access to
    these free license computer programs could change the lives of many
    people, including the artists their families at Sisonkwe.</para>

    <para>Some of the artists now use the GIMP (Graphical Image Manipulation
    Program), an open source graphics program, to do sketches and rough
    diagrams of the work that they will do on canvas or in clay. Others are
    using a whole operating system, like the Suse Linux distribution, to run
    their computers (as they couldn't afford the upgrade prices of what they
    were running). The Freedom Toaster Wisdom project in Gabarone has touched
    the lives of over 3000 people already. Most of them are high school or
    university students who have needed access to computer software so that
    they can type projects, send emails, work on programming, or read
    literature (like Shakespeare's plays).</para>

    <para>Amai Ndodwa doesn't wear a leopard skin, but she does tell the story
    of the how the leopard earned his spots, and then she tells her audience
    of the many different ways that we can help save and share wisdom. The
    Freedom Toaster is high on her list, as she tells her audiences of the
    lives that have changed and the people who have also changed because they
    access to that information.</para>

    <para>The Sisonkwe Community Art Centre has seen many painting affect the
    lives of people who come and view them. They are now seeing how the
    Freedom Toaster project is doing the same.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Flagstaff, Arizona - USA</title>

    <para>[This letter is a projection, Cecile Owen is a fictional
    character]</para>

    <para>Dear Editor,</para>

    <para>My name is Cecile Owens, and I'm a science teacher at Kennedy High
    in Flagstaff, Arizona. I have taught there for the last seven years, and
    have seen some very bright students come and go, some made it in the big
    world, others tried to take an easy road and found that it didn't get them
    anywhere. At the end of last year I was down and weary of teaching.
    Kennedy High has a lot of students from the poorer parts of town, as well
    as some from the more affluent areas. We have school gangs. I have to wear
    a 'panic' button on me when I come to school, just in case I need to call
    security to deal with a situation (it also is part of my protection). The
    usual drug sub-culture exists, but it's hard to tell who's dealing as they
    seem to change weekly. Last year I had nine of my students end up in
    juvenile court, six of them had community service judgements given. The
    other three are in juvenile detention.</para>

    <para>I'm happy to say that this year is looking much better. It is this
    change for the better that I wanted to write you and your magazine about,
    and about something called a 'Freedom Toaster'.</para>

    <para>One of my students, Clara Falenzo, is a great example of this
    positive change. She has been making A's and B's all through her school
    career here at Kennedy High. She lives in one of the project houses a few
    blocks from the school. Her Mom looks after her and her younger brother,
    David, as a single working parent. I know that money is always tight, but
    they have been able to save up enough to buy a second hand computer and
    printer. They planned to use it for all the typing assignments that Clara
    was getting, but very soon found all sorts of other uses for it, thanks to
    the school's Freedom Toaster....</para>

    <para>For those of your readers who don't know what a Freedom Toaster is,
    let me tell them a little bit about it, so that they understand why I'm so
    excited.</para>

    <para>A Freedom Toaster is a computer that is set up like a vending
    machine. It has three (sometimes four) CD/DVD writing drives, and a hard
    drive that contains CD burnable images of free and open source software
    (FOSS), like Linux operating systems, the OpenOffice.org office suite, web
    browsers, email programs, graphics, programs, games, star position
    programs, and programming tools. It also has other free license software
    and information. The system is navigated through the use of a touch screen
    menu and information system. It was first thought of and built in South
    Africa (supported by the Shuttleworth Foundation). There it was originally
    used as a 'bandwidth substitute', specific Internet content available
    where the Internet was not. In Arizona the State Education Department has
    included the curriculum for each year of school, along with free license
    applications and texts that can be used to supplement the
    curriculum.</para>

    <para>When Carla's mother arrived home with the news that they could go
    pick up the computer from the post office (mail order), Carla was
    overjoyed. She told me about getting all the boxes onto the bus and
    lugging them home, and then the fun of connecting everything together.
    Carla isn't a stranger to computers, as she regularly uses the computer
    lab here at school (5 computers, one with Internet and email). I didn't
    think about the Freedom Toaster project when she told me this, but the
    week after their delivery I started teaching one the courses that was on
    the 'Teach Arizona!' CD images available on the Toaster. Each of the
    students were given a blank CD and instructions to toast their own copies
    to use when assigned homework and for personal research.</para>

    <para>Carla cornered me the next day as I was coming out of my class, and
    excitedly asked whether I knew what else was on the Freedom Toaster. I
    didn't then, but now I do. Carla began to toast all sorts of things, like
    the Linux Red Hat Fedora Core operating system or the OpenOffice.org suite
    of office programs (word processor, spreadsheet, database, etc), She even
    did some of the programming tutorials that came as part of the various
    operating systems and started changing some of the original (source) code,
    customising it to her particular needs. I suggested that she take Computer
    Sciences as she seemed to be just gobbling all the computer information
    up.</para>

    <para>That was a year ago. Carla has now won a full scholarship to UCLA in
    their computer programming department. She won it on the grounds of her
    computer science project of last semester where she made her own operating
    system, based on Linux. Two of her classmates have also won scholarships
    to other Universities, also based on projects from the Freedom
    Toaster.</para>

    <para>There is a new feeling in our school this year. One which whispers
    in the students' ears 'you could be next!!' They all make use of the
    Freedom Toaster, and are constantly asking all the teachers when the next
    updates will be available. No one has gone to juvenile detention this
    year. I'm having fun again as a teacher.</para>

    <para>Yours sincerely</para>

    <para>Miss C Owens</para>
  </sect1>
</article>