<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
	<title>Freedom Toaster - want a slice?</title>
	<para>The Internet has been hailed as a <quote>great equaliser</quote> (Brynjolfsson and Smith
		2000) of developing and developed nations. There are however, <quote>great disparities in
			opportunity to access the Internet, the information and the educational/business
			opportunities tied to this</quote> (wikipedia.org, 07.10.05).</para>
	<para>Billions of people live with restrictive telecommunications environments that make it
		difficult and costly to access digital products such as free software and educational
		content. The Freedom Toaster project was started in 2004 by the Shuttleworth Foundation as a
		way to overcome these problems. </para>
	<para>Freedom Toasters are conveniently located, self-contained, computer-based, &apos;Bring
		'n Burn&apos; facilities. Like vending machines, preloaded to dispense confectionery,
		Freedom Toasters are preloaded to dispense free digital products.</para>
	<orderedlist>
		<para>Obtaining a product is as simple as 1, 2, 3:</para>
		<listitem>
			<para>Bring writable CD or DVD media to the Freedom Toaster.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Insert into the Freedom Toasters' CD/DVD drive.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Select the product to duplicate.</para>
		</listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	<para>Unlike the vending machine, where people pay to obtain perishable consumable products.
		Freedom Toasters dispense new information, communication technologies, software and content
		that act as a catalyst for increasing people’s choice and are directly translatable into
		knowledge, leading to greater freedom.</para>
	<para>Whilst a chocolate bar is consumed by one person, Freedom Toaster wares carry no
		restrictions. In fact, people are encouraged to make further copies and to distribute them,
		enabling the whole community to benefit.</para>
	<sect1>
		<title>Freedom Toasters in Society</title>
		<para>Freedom Toasters are suitable for use by any organisation in any venue, for any
			purpose. Businesses, educational institutions, government departments, libraries and
			NGOs can all accelerate their mandates.</para>
		<para>Creating a list describing the purposes for which Freedom Toasters can be put to use,
			would stretch even the most fervent of imaginations, topical examples include the
			distribution of:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>information for major awareness campaigns such as HIV/AIDS, polio,
					tuberculosis, malaria and other diseases;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>information to satisfy governmental obligations for human rights compliance
					such as access to information;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>skills-based, self-help, multimedia training programs on topics such as such
					as improving maternal health, environmental sustainability and many more health
					and agricultural related topics;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>distribution of free software such as free computing environments,
					communications software and business packages;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>distribution of educational literature for personal growth such as information
					pertaining to the promotion of gender equality and womans empowerment or
					computer training courses that improve job prospects;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>curriculum aligned content disseminated directly from Departments of Education
					for teachers in rural schools.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>Freedom Toasters transcend the gaps that cause the <quote>digital divide</quote> by
			acting as low-tech digital gateways between the <quote>haves</quote> and <quote>have
				nots</quote> of the world.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Touch and Go</title>
		<para>The main interface of the Freedom Toaster is a touchscreen liquid crystal display and
			an intuitive software interface. The software is designed to work as an off-the-shelf
			package that <quote>Just Works</quote>.</para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/home.png" align="center" format="PNG" depth="8cm"
					scalefit="1"/>
			</imageobject>
			<caption>The Main Screen</caption>
		</mediaobject>
		<para>The main screen is one of several that cycle when the Freedom Toaster is not in use.
			Each screen provides information answering the common questions people have during their
			first encounter with a Freedom Toaster. From this screen people can see the Freedom
			Toasters main product categories.</para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/prosncons.png" align="center" format="PNG" depth="8cm"
					scalefit="1"/>
			</imageobject>
			<caption>Product Information Screens</caption>
		</mediaobject>
		<para>Objective information about each of the products is made available. Touching the
				<guibutton>Previous</guibutton> or the <guibutton>Next</guibutton> button, people
			can browse the information provided at their leisure to make informed choices about what
			they would like to duplicate. Helpful information such as the number of CD/DVDs required
			ensures that people are prepared before making a selection.</para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/burning.png" align="center" format="PNG" depth="8cm"
					scalefit="1"/>
			</imageobject>
			<caption>Progress Feedback Screen</caption>
		</mediaobject>
		<para>When selections are made and burning commences, the Freedom Toaster provides feedback
			of the current progress for each of the CD/DVD devices loaded with writable media.</para>
		<para>The entire Freedom Toaster interaction is designed as a <quote>Touch and Go</quote>
			experience that results in instant gratification the moment the CD/DVD writer ejects a
			duplicated media.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Benefits</title>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>No need for Internet access</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Easy-to-deploy</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Easy-to-access</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Easy-to-use</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Screensaver cycles through content</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Touch screen operation</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Customisable interface options</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Localizable interface texts</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Capable of serving local and tailored content</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Three CD/DVD writer devices</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Freedom Toaster is a Free and Open Source project</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>It's as easy as toast!</title>
		<para>To discover a Freedom Toaster near you or learn how to build one of your own, visit
			the Freedom Toaster <ulink url="http://www.freedomtoaster.org">web site</ulink> and join
			the community.</para>
		<para>Visit the <ulink url="http://www.shuttleworthfoundation.org">Shuttleworth
			Foundation</ulink>, to find out more about their involvement in education and philosophy
			about open source.</para>
	</sect1>
</article>
