<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
	<title>Whitepaper</title>
	<subtitle>The UN Perspective</subtitle>
	<sect1>
		<title>The Freedom Toaster</title>
		<para>It was just over a decade ago when Netscape floated and brought the World Wide Web
			into the office, classroom and home, changing us from passive consumers of information,
			to active participators.</para>
		<para>Societies and economies have boomed due to the sharing of information. Both business
			and learning have found commercial and cultural communities to interact with –
			instantly. Knowledge has always driven the ability to attain and maintain wealth, in the
				21<superscript>st</superscript> century this has never been more real.</para>
		<para>Whilst the Internet has been hailed as a &quot;great equalizer&quot;
			(Brynjolfsson and Smith 2000) of developing and developed nations there are however,
			&quot;great disparities in opportunity to access the Internet, the information and
			the educational/business opportunities tied to this&quot; (wikipedia.org, 07.10.05).</para>
		<para>Due to poor quality and costly infrastructures, the knowledge gap, and all that that
			implies, is widening. This knowledge gap is not just prevalent between developed and
			developing countries, but is also seen in poor rural areas of the Western world.
			This is inhibiting education, commerce and good health practice for all.</para>
		<para>The Freedom Toaster acts as an equaliser.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>What is the Freedom Toaster?</title>
		<informaltable frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<colspec colnum="1" align="left"/>
				<colspec colnum="3" align="center"/>
				<tbody>
					<row valign="top">
						<entry>
							<para>The Freedom Toaster is both a concept and a physical machine. As a
								concept, the Freedom Toaster is a bandwidth substitute. It is a way
								of moving massive amounts of information from a variety of sources,
								including the Internet, to the remote end user without the
								infrastructure that is usually required. Currently it is a system
								for disseminating Free and Open Source Software (FOSS) and content
								(operating systems, productivity and business software, community
								e-books, e-learning packages). In physical form the Freedom Toaster
								is a low cost computer, with CD/DVD-burning devices and a web
								browser enabled touch screen interface assembled into what looks
								like a vending machine.</para>
						</entry>
						<entry align="center">
							<inlinemediaobject>
								<imageobject>
									<imagedata fileref="../images/freedom_toaster1.jpg"
										format="JPEG" depth="7cm" scalefit="1" align="center"/>
								</imageobject>
							</inlinemediaobject>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row valign="top">
						<entry>
							<para>The name &quot;Freedom Toaster&quot; was chosen because it
								uses Linux, a free license Operating System, and within the language
								of Linux users the act of burning a CD is termed
								&quot;toasting&quot;. However, it later became apparent that
								the name had a deeper meaning than originally intended. It
								encapsulates the philosophy of FOSS. We have the freedom to choose
								which software we use, we have the freedom to change it if we want
								to, and we have the freedom to share it with anyone, for free.</para>
							<para>The Shuttleworth Foundation created and invested in the Freedom
								Toaster project to further its mandate of driving innovation. Mark
								Shuttleworth, the foundations' founder, believes that &quot;if
								we are to lift Africa from her current circumstances, we will need a
								generation of learners that are gifted with curiosity about the
								world in which they live, and the tools to understand and shape that
								world&quot;.</para>
							<para>To do this, they need access to information.</para>
						</entry>
						<entry align="center">
							<inlinemediaobject>
								<imageobject>
									<imagedata fileref="../images/toaster_proto.jpg" format="JPEG"
										depth="8cm" scalefit="1" align="center"/>
								</imageobject>
							</inlinemediaobject>
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</informaltable>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>The importance of the Freedom Toaster</title>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">The situation</emphasis> - In many parts of the world,
			particularly in the developing world, there is a lack of communication infrastructure
			and access to high technology. Whilst many in the developed world are able to use the
			Internet to communicate in education, business and recreation, this is not the case in
			regions such as Africa, South America, or Asia. The Internet World Stats Report (23rd
			July 2005) states that in Africa only 1.8% of the population are Internet users. In
			Latin America/Caribbean the figure is 12.5% and Asia is 8.9%. It is evident that these
			populations do not benefit from the advantages that the Internet can give. Even if there
			is access, it is often costly, of low bandwidth and quality. This prevents downloading
			of the type of software and content that is available on the Freedom Toaster.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">The difference - now</emphasis> - Like many new concepts it is
			important to understand the need that inspired the Freedom Toaster. It is equally
			important to understand how the concept has developed, and what the possibilities may
			be, both now and in the future. Freedom Toasters are currently available in sub-Saharan
			Africa and although the number of Freedom Toaster's is only in double digits and the
			system is still in its infancy, we can see the real difference in people's lives.</para>
		<para>Through the hosting of Freedom Toasters, FOSS and content is made available to
			everyone, regardless of colour, race, creed, religion, sexual orientation, class,
			economic background, or political affiliation.</para>
		<para>The Internet user who does not have the bandwidth to download a full operating system
			to use on their computer can now go to a Freedom Toaster and burn one of the 13
			different distributions of Linux currently available. This frees the person from the
			frustration and cost of spending hours online waiting for a download (that may be
			corrupted due to poor local connectivity) and then burning the CDs. It also saves the
			countries limited bandwidth from continued downloads of the same files.</para>
		<para>The person who has no access to the Internet but has a computer can now burn an
			operating system, the OpenOffice.org productivity suite (immediately benefiting from the
			word processor and spreadsheet applications), or the Project Gutenberg CD/DVD and
			utilise them at no extra cost.</para>
		<para>The Teachers can use the material on the Freedom Toaster to learn content for
			themselves, and then teach what they have learnt. This could be the prefect distribution
			tool for Departments of Education - ensuring that all teachers have curriculum aligned
			materials to teach from.</para>
		<para>A computer user who has used pirated software can erase all of all their illegal
			software and install an up-to-date operating system that will provide all the necessary
			tools they need to accomplish their computing tasks.</para>
		<para>If an entrepreneur wishes to make money from their computer, by running an
			import-export business, an accountancy practise, or a printing works, they are going to
			need software specifically designed for the task. This doesn't come cheap. There is FOSS
			software that fulfils all the criteria, available on the Internet, but these packages
			are large, even by broadband standards, and not much good to someone who hasn't even got
			a phone. With access to the Freedom Toaster the business person now has access to this
			software, just for the price of the blank CDs.</para>
		<para>General computer knowledge is increased by having Freedom Toasters in public places
			(libraries, community centres, science/technology centres). For many people, computer
			literacy is one of the key knowledge areas needed to find a better job. The Freedom
			Toaster provides access to FOSS operating systems and productivity software that can be
			used to train people how to use a computer, how to type, and how to write documents,
			spreadsheets, and other documents. Computer literacy is improved, and more of the
			digital divide is crossed.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">The difference - future</emphasis> - It is difficult to know
			what will happen in the future, but there are specific trends that can be traced, and
			predictions made. We can also imagine what the future will hold by asking ourselves
			where we would want the world to be, and what would be different if a project such as
			the Freedom Toaster proliferated across the developing world.</para>
		<para>Gartner, a world renowned technology/business analysis and research company, in their
			report entitled 'Gartners' Positions on the Five Hottest IT Topics and Trends in 2005',
			tells us that Open Source Software (OSS) (a subset of FOSS) is a catalyst that will
			restructure the IT industry, producing higher-quality software at a lower cost. They
			predict that it won't destroy industry giants, such as IBM and Microsoft, but that it
			will revolutionise software markets by moving revenue streams from license fees to
			services and support.</para>
		<para>Gartner warns that OSS strategies must address the unique characteristics of
			individual markets and the differences in open-source license models. The Freedom
			Toaster is one way of addressing OSS strategy within markets that have low (or no)
			Internet penetration. The report by Gartner states that &quot;through 2005, OSS
			products will account for no more than 10 percent of the portfolio of Global 2000
			companies, but by 2008, 95 percent of Global 2000 organisations will have formal
			open-source acquisition and management strategies that address the challenges and
			opportunities that OSS introduces&quot;. If that many Global 2000 organisations will
			be involved at some level, then access to FOSS will bring greater involvement in the
			global economy and will create real opportunities for disadvantaged communities.</para>
		<para>In 10 years time the world of computer software will be a completely different place.
			Through projects like the Freedom Toaster, people could have access to FOSS and choose
			this instead of piracy. Computer software companies could be making their profits from
			offering technical support for FOSS projects and services instead of licenses for
			operating systems and proprietary programs - opening up the market for small businesses
			and aiding economic growth in rural developing nations.</para>
		<para>In 15 years time the influence of FOSS may have changed the technical inequalities of
			the developed and developing worlds. This means that the high school student in SOWETO
			could customise an email system as part of a school project. When she graduates from
			high school she could go on to become a high powered programmer for a major corporation
			or enterprise. Or a student in Bogot&#225;, learning an accountancy package can take
			the software with him when leaving school and set up his own business.</para>
		<para>Having easy access to free license software could change so many people's lives for
			the better. Teachers can have content, businesses can keep their books, entertainers,
			programmers, musicians, writers, journalists, students, governments, multimedia
			producers, and even cooks and cleaners could live better lives because of the influence
			of something as simple as a Freedom Toaster.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>What is the role of the Freedom Toaster in context of global development efforts?</title>
		<para>The Freedom Toaster is a simple solution to a seemingly impossible problem - access.
			By enabling access, we can help lift the barrier to educational content and start to
			create a level playing field for the developing world.</para>
		<itemizedlist mark="endash">
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Access to information as a human right</emphasis>
				</para>
				<para>One of the fundamental principles that the Freedom Toaster addresses is the
					idea that access to information is a basic human right. In many places around
					the world information is inaccessible. The Freedom Toaster project creates a
					vehicle for improving that access. It provides a platform for distributing
					information and software to allow you to use and learn from it.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Social and economic growth</emphasis>
				</para>
				<para>Access to the texts of the Project Gutenberg, and to other distributable
					content (like awareness programs, community educational material and general
					reference data on wikipedia.org) will enable teachers to better educate children
					and communities, resulting in greater opportunities to prosper.</para>
				<para>This better educated community will also enable small and medium sized
					businesses to run with lower start-up and operating costs by using the FOSS
					provided on the Freedom Toaster. Access to the source code will mean greater
					customisation to local conditions by local programmers, ensuring that businesses
					can be efficient, flexible and get the best from their tools.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<itemizedlist mark="endash">
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Development</emphasis>
				</para>
				<para>The 'digital divide' is a key development issue. The Freedom Toaster provides
					a vehicle for accessing FOSS where there is low or no Internet access, and this
					brings digital information that requires high-bandwidth to a low digital
					penetration area.</para>
				<para>The ability to access information is relatively high in the developed world -
					compulsive schooling, public libraries, media. The developing world is not able
					to compete on this scale, either in terms of education or business. Virtual
					classrooms are not an option for most in these regions, but virtual classroom
					information could be made available through the vehicle of a Freedom Toaster. </para>
				<para>The use of the software distributed by the Freedom Toaster will also create
					markets and demand. Once more people are computer literate there will be a
					greater demand for better communications infrastructure, and an increased demand
					for other basic community needs.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Empowerment</emphasis>
				</para>
				<para>The Freedom Toaster can be used as a tool to provide a means of empowerment.
					Knowledge brings empowerment, and so access to knowledge brings the potential of
					empowerment.</para>
				<para>Women in Kabul would potentially have the same access and empowerment
					opportunities as those in London. Men in Chile would have similar access and
					opportunities to benefit from the open source movement as someone in the United
					States or Europe.</para>
				<para>Children in Sucre, Bolivia or in the disadvantaged northern inner-city areas
					of the United Kingdom can have the same educational resources as Perth,
					Australia. The potential of increased and equal access to FOSS, tutorials,
					encyclopedias, and other reference materials (like the US CIA World Fact Book
					contained in the Project Gutenberg and all of the collaborative content provided
					on wikipedia.org) will bring higher quality education and greater empowerment
					for teachers as well as students.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Infrastructure</emphasis>
				</para>
				<para>High quality operating systems and business productivity software (both office
					and Internet) are the virtual infrastructure of the information age - something
					that is denied in areas of no real infrastructure. The Freedom Toaster
					instantaneously solves this problem.</para>
				<para>The potential infrastructure provided by access to a Freedom Toaster goes
					beyond the software that it distributes. The general educational value and
					computer literacy increase is a vital part of the virtual infrastructure;
					ensuring that people are not left behind due to their geographic
				location.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Free and Legal vs. Culture of Piracy</emphasis>
				</para>
				<para>The Freedom Toaster addresses the issue of piracy by providing a high quality
					alternative. According to the Software Piracy Study done by the Business
					Software Association of Australia in 2004, an estimated 86% of software
					installed on the computers in Zimbabwe was pirated. In India the figure was at
					73%, in Brazil 61%, in South Africa 36%.</para>
				<para>For every two dollars worth of software purchased legitimately, one dollar
					worth is obtained illegally. In economic terms, this costs a country local
					business and revenue, and increases costs of policing and policy creation.</para>
				<para>With FOSS there is no need for a culture of piracy. The operating systems use
					free licenses. Within the open source arena people can also access the code and
					develop it to suit their own needs, or develop it in cooperation with
				others.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">Literacy</emphasis>
				</para>
				<para>Literacy is the passport for full participation in today's society. Anyone who
					cannot read or write will face difficulties in finding work, managing their
					health, raising children, and coping with simple, every-day tasks such as
					shopping and paying bills. Illiterate adults are often excluded from political
					and social processes, and as such, are denied the chance to exercise their
					rights and fulfil their responsibilities as citizens. Yet nearly one seventh of
					the world's population is illiterate.</para>
				<para>Worldwide figures released by UNESCO in August 2005 indicate that 784.8
					million adults over the age of 15 cannot read or write. Even more alarming is
					that just under two thirds are women.</para>
				<para>Educational aptitude and abilities rise with the proliferation of information
					- improving literacy problems in the developing world.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>The concepts contained in the Freedom Toaster project and the software that it
			distributes help tackle many of the problems faced by the developing world, and even
			some faced in the developed world.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Implementation</title>
		<para>The Shuttleworth Foundation has provided the resources to take the idea of the Freedom
			Toaster and make it a reality. Now the project needs to go where it is really needed -
			the rest of the world.</para>
		<para>The first stage is educating people about the Freedom Toaster concept. Community
			project directors, Head Librarian's, Science Centre committees, and other organisations
			and leaders are being approached with the possibility of hosting a Freedom Toaster.</para>
		<para>The Shuttleworth Foundation drives social innovation by piloting projects and then
			establishing information channels that explain successes and promote replication. By
			giving people the tools to create, implement, maintain, market and develop Freedom
			Toasters it is hoped that the project will grow wings and help disadvantaged communities
			in all four corners of the world.</para>
		<sect2>
			<title>Where?</title>
			<para>The list of where to host a Freedom Toaster should almost be endless, in South
				Africa they are based in:</para>
			<itemizedlist mark="endash">
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis role="bold">Schools</emphasis>
					</para>
					<para>A school that hosts a Freedom Toaster will have access to the latest
						educational material. With access to the FOSS content the interest of
						students at the school would also become more highly focused on Information
						Technology and all the advantages that brings - both in the classroom and
						later on in life.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para></para>
			<itemizedlist mark="endash">
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis role="bold">Libraries</emphasis>
					</para>
					<para>The Freedom Toaster currently contains both Project Gutenberg and
						wikipedia.org. This collection of text based files contains literature from
						around the world. It is a collection of fact and fiction, high literature
						(poetry, plays, operas), scientific texts (Darwin's 'Origin of the Species'
						or Einstein's works on relativity), philosophy, religious texts, and
						reference works. Having this project available in libraries will increase
						exposure to world class literature and will increase learning and education
						for those who are wanting to learn.</para>
					<para>The only limit to the information available is copyright law – anything
						else a library would want can be hosted.</para>
					<para>A library will also receive a public service benefit by hosting a Freedom
						Toaster. The members of the library will gain access to world class software
						and information.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis role="bold">Science Centres, and Science/Technology
						Expositions</emphasis>
					</para>
					<para>One of the goals of science centres is to engage the minds of those who
						visit them with science and technology. Hosting a Freedom Toaster provides a
						discussion point for the computer science topic and FOSS principles. It also
						provides a community focus in that people have free access to the operating
						systems and other software available around from the world.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis role="bold">Shopping Malls and Retail Outlets</emphasis>
					</para>
					<para>Increased and prolonged footfall in shopping malls is attained furthering
						their business directive.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>The importance of hosting a Freedom Toaster is not just the benefit that the
				hosting location receives, but more particularly the benefit to the community. The
				key is access. Everyone must be able to access the Freedom Toaster, free of charge
				within reasonable hours in order to burn what they require from it.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>When?</title>
			<para>The needs and problems that the Freedom Toaster addresses are needs and problems
				that require an immediate response. There is no other answer to the question of when
				to implement than &apos;now!&apos;. People can have access to the FOSS and
				content distributed by the Freedom Toaster, it is their right.</para>
			<para>There are over 2 billion young people alive in the world today, most of them in
				developing countries, and they are demanding access to the technological wonders of
				our age. While the Freedom Toaster project does not directly address the problem of
				getting computers into impoverished and low Internet access communities, it does
				address the problem of access to the information that the Internet brings. If
				projects like this are not implemented soon, many of these young people will be
				disadvantaged and will seek other means of engagement in the information age.</para>
		</sect2>
		<?pagebreak?>
		<sect2>
			<title>How?</title>
			<para>The Shuttleworth Foundation is creating documentation of how to build a Freedom
				Toaster - The Freedom Toaster CookBook. The CookBook describes in detail each phase
				of putting the Freedom Toaster together and loading the required software. This
				information is freely available to anyone and will be ready for use from March 2006.
				The idea of the Freedom Toaster can be adapted to many other circumstances by using
				the basic construction information contained in this document.</para>
			<para>An educational campaign is also taking place, first for people and institutions to
				host Freedom Toasters, then for people who will have access to a Freedom Toaster.
				Computer User Groups and volunteers have been part of this process to date, but more
				needs to happen if the full benefits of the Freedom Toaster concept are to be
				realised. Leaders and champions within communities then need to have the Freedom
				Toaster built and securely placed in the hosting locations.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Future of the Toaster</title>
		<para>We believe that we can prevent economic status from being the deciding factor in
			access to information.</para>
		<para>We want to see Freedom Toasters helping to set up businesses in Kinshasa, giving
			university students' vital thesis content in Oslo and allowing teachers to get
			scientific reference material in Santiago. The Freedom Toaster is a community based and
			enabled project and therefore the future of the toaster has to belong to the future of
			communities - the world.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>More information</title>
		<para>For more information on where you can find a Freedom Toaster, joining the Freedom
			Toaster community or building one of your own, please visit: www.freedomtoaster.org or
			contact info@freedomtoaster.org. </para>
		<para>For more information on the Shuttleworth Foundation, their involvement education and
			their open source philosophy, please visit www.shuttleworthfoundation.org.</para>
		<para>The Freedom Toaster was created from an idea of one of the employees of the
			Shuttleworth Foundation.  We would like to thank Jason Hudson for his effort, creativity
			and passion.</para>
	</sect1>
</article>
