<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Freedom Toaster Website Home Page Update</title>
  <sect1>
    <title>Home Page</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">What is the Freedom Toaster?</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>The Internet has been hailed as a <quote>great equaliser</quote> (Brynjolfsson and Smith
      2000) of developing and developed nations. There are however, <quote>great disparities in
        opportunity to access the Internet, the information and the educational/business
        opportunities tied to this</quote> (wikipedia.org, 07.10.05).</para>
    <para>Billions of people live with restrictive telecommunications environments that make it
      difficult and costly to access digital products such as free software and educational content.
      The Freedom Toaster project was started in 2004 by the Shuttleworth Foundation as a way to
      overcome these problems.</para>
    <para>Freedom Toasters are conveniently located, self-contained, computer-based, 'Bring 'n Burn'
      facilities. Like vending machines, preloaded to dispense confectionery, Freedom Toasters are
      preloaded to dispense free digital products (e.g. Linux Operating Systems and the
      OpenOffice.org office suite)[Link to Toaster Software].</para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">But why do we need this?</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>The Freedom Toaster project began as a means of overcoming the difficulty in obtaining
      Linux and Open Source software due to the restrictive telecommunications environment in South
      Africa, where the easy downloading of large pieces of software is just not possible.</para>
    <para>Benefits...</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>No need for Internet access.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Easy-to-deploy.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Easy-to-access.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Easy-to-use.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Screensaver cycles through content.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Touch screen operation.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Customisable interface options.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Localizable interface texts.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Capable of serving local and tailored content.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Four CD/DVD writer devices.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Freedom Toaster is a Free and Open Source project.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">And the name? What's up with that?</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>Initially the name came about directly as a result of the fact that Linux is a free
      Operating System and that you &rdquor;toast&rdquo; a CD with Linux. However, it later
      became apparent that, the name actually captured a meaning deeper than what was originally
      intended. It encapsulates the philosophy of Open Source Software, that we have the freedom to
      choose which software we use, that we have the freedom to change it if we like and that we
      have the freedom to share it with anyone, for free. Listen closely....and you'll hear violins
      playing in the background</para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Free for all!</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>In the past, most people have shied away from Open Source Software, more particularly
      Operating Systems. Because, unless you were already an expert on various "scary" details that
      accompanied them, it&rsquo;s been notoriously difficult to get your hands on reliable and
      complete distributions that were easy to install and easy to upgrade. Not anymore, now
      it&rsquo;s as easy as toast.</para>
    <para>Freedom Toasters are suitable for use by any organisation in any venue, for any purpose.
      Businesses, educational institutions, government departments, libraries and NGOs can all
      accelerate their mandates. [Links to Educational Resources page (White papers, Case Studies,
      Brochure, and User Cases)]</para>
    <para>Creating a list describing the purposes for which Freedom Toasters can be put to use,
      would stretch even the most fervent of imaginations, topical examples include the distribution
      of:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>information for major awareness campaigns such as HIV/AIDS, polio, tuberculosis,
          malaria and other diseases;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>information to satisfy governmental obligations for human rights compliance such as
          access to information;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>skills-based, self-help, multimedia training programs on topics such as such as
          improving maternal health, environmental sustainability and many more health and
          agricultural related topics;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>distribution of free software such as free computing environments, communications
          software and business packages;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>distribution of educational literature for personal growth such as information
          pertaining to the promotion of gender equality and womans empowerment or computer training
          courses that improve job prospects;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>curriculum aligned content disseminated directly from Departments of Education for
          teachers in rural schools.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Freedom Toasters transcend the gaps that cause the <quote>digital divide</quote> by acting
      as low-tech digital gateways between the <quote>haves</quote> and <quote>have nots</quote> of
      the world.</para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">How do I use the Toaster?</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>Obviously the first thing to do is find out where the closest Freedom Toaster is [Link to
      Toaster Locations] , and then get yourself there. The way to obtain a product from the Toaster
      is as simple as 1, 2, 3:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Bring writable CD or DVD media to the Freedom Toaster.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Insert into the Freedom Toasters' CD/DVD drive.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the product to duplicate.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>On-screen information tells you more about the software you have selected, including how
      many CDs you will need. The Freedom Toasters also contain a host of on-screen information to
      teach people a little more about the world of Free and Open software. Touch the screen, browse
      and explore!</para>
    <para>Unlike the vending machine, where people pay to obtain perishable consumable products.
      Freedom Toasters dispense new information, communication technologies, software and content
      that act as a catalyst for increasing people&rsquo;s choice and are directly translatable
      into knowledge, leading to greater freedom.</para>
    <para>Whilst a chocolate bar is consumed by one person, Freedom Toaster wares carry no
      restrictions. In fact, people are encouraged to make further copies and to distribute them,
      enabling the whole community to benefit.</para>
    <para>Click here for a more detailed view of using the Freedom Toaster  [Link to Touch and Go]</para>
  </sect1>
</article>
