<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Freedom Toaster Website Update</title>
  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>Having written the white papers, case studies, brochure, and user cases we now have an
      opportunity to present them on the website (and incorporate them on a Freedom Toaster Info
      CD...)</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>These two sections set out the ideas behind the update for the website.</para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Document Purposes:</title>
      <para>In order to place the various documents within the Freedom Toaster website we need to
        understand the purpose of each type of document and then create a place for that purpose on
        the website.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>User Cases</para>
          <para>The main purpose of the user cases is to show potential hosts the possible benefits
            of their hosting a Freedom Toaster. The secondary purpose of the user cases is to show
            the benefits of the Freedom Toaster to the communities that have access to one.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>White Papers</para>
          <para>The purpose of the white papers is to inform specific audiences about the potential
            for positive change within communities through the proliferation of Freedom Toasters and
            an advertisement for using/joiining the project.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Case Studies</para>
          <para>The purpose of the Case Studies is to present the Freedom Toaster as a viable,
            working technology for the dissemination of digital electronic information.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Brochure</para>
          <para>The purpose of the brochure is to present information about the Freedom Toaster to
            the general public. To inform the reader about what the Freedom Toaster is, why it was
            developed, how it works, and where to go for more information.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>The purpose of presenting these documents on the Freedom Toaster website is to increase
        awareness of what the Freedom Toaster is and how it can be used to benefit communities. It's
        first purpose is therefore to educate those visiting the site. The second purpose of having
        these documents available is so that they can be downloaded and used to promote Freedom
        Toaster awareness in different communities around the world.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Website Presentation</title>
      <para>With these purposes in mind, these are the areas that need to be developed/created</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>An "Educational Resources" page that has PDFs of the brochure, case studies, and
            white papers, with links to subpages containing the white papers, the case studies, and
            the user cases.</para>
          <para>The purpose of this page is to present the website user with tools to educate
            themselves and those around them.</para>
          <para>see 'educational.xml'.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A news article "Freedom Toaster In Action" update. Informs the reader about the FT
            presentation to the UN, the production of the educational material (brochure and user
            cases), and the production of specific case studies.</para>
          <para>see section below 'Freedom Toaster In Action'</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Incorporation of the brochure material into the 'home' page.</para>
          <para>see 'homepage.xml'</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Incorporation of the user cases, case studies, and white papers through out the
            website</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Freedom Toaster In Action</title>
    <para>News article about the presentation of the White Paper to the UN...</para>
  </sect1>
</article>
