<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Freedom Toaster Website Update</title>
    <sect1>
      <title>Touch and Go</title>
      <para>The main interface of the Freedom Toaster is a touchscreen liquid crystal display and an
        intuitive software interface. The software is designed to work as an off-the-shelf package
        that <quote>Just Works</quote>.</para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" depth="8cm" fileref="images/home.png" format="PNG" scalefit="1"
          />
        </imageobject>
        <caption>The Main Screen</caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <para>The main screen is one of several that cycle when the Freedom Toaster is not in use.
        Each screen provides information answering the common questions people have during their
        first encounter with a Freedom Toaster. From this screen people can see the Freedom Toasters
        main product categories.</para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" depth="8cm" fileref="images/prosncons.png" format="PNG"
            scalefit="1"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>Product Information Screens</caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <para>Objective information about each of the products is made available. Touching the
          <guibutton>Previous</guibutton> or the <guibutton>Next</guibutton> button, people can
        browse the information provided at their leisure to make informed choices about what they
        would like to duplicate. Helpful information such as the number of CD/DVDs required ensures
        that people are prepared before making a selection.</para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" depth="8cm" fileref="images/burning.png" format="PNG"
            scalefit="1"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>Progress Feedback Screen</caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <para>When selections are made and burning commences, the Freedom Toaster provides feedback of
        the current progress for each of the CD/DVD devices loaded with writable media.</para>
      <para>The entire Freedom Toaster interaction is designed as a <quote>Touch and Go</quote>
        experience that results in instant gratification the moment the CD/DVD writer ejects a
        duplicated media.</para>
  </sect1>
</article>
